Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan and today we're going to
be learning about solution stoichiometry.
Specifically, we're going to look about
how to find molarity, volume, and mass.
So when exactly do you have to use this?
So solution stoichiometry is all about
aqueous solutions and when you are trying
to mix them together to try to solve for
volumes, masses, using molarity to try to
do different stoichiometric conversions.
Using using a balanced chemical equation,
these can tend to be the hardest, uh,
stoichiometric equations to do just
because it has to use that concept of
molarity, which, as we know, is moles
over liters and can be very, very
challenging to try to really master.
So we're gonna go through the
steps and tips and tricks of how to
solve these going through different
examples of problems that you may
see in your introductory chemistry
course, uh, to be able to try to
help you solve them in your course.
Alright, so let's go take a
look at the different steps.
So when we're doing these reactions,
the first thing that we need to do
is when it comes to the steps is
balancing the chemical equation.
So sometimes this may involve
predicting the chemical equation.
The good news is that most
solution equations typically are
double replacement reactions.
So, you're going to be doing that inside
outside bonding together, and balancing
them usually is some of the easier
types of ones to balance, especially
when you compare them to combustion,
which tend to be really difficult.
Now, after that, you always want to,
after you check if it's balanced, if
you generally see coefficients, that
means it's already done for you, then
you want to write down your mole ratios
that are important for your problem and
all the given information that you have.
This may include volumes,
molarities, masses.
And it's really important to try
to stay organized while doing it.
I'll go through exactly how I
usually go through these problems
so that you can stay organized too.
Being organized is crucial because it's
very easy to accidentally mix terms up.
So read the word problems carefully and
make sure you sort things out as you go.
Um, the last step is always
let your units guide you.
It's always generally helpful to have like
a molar map to help guide the way that
you're going to be canceling out units.
So I'll be showing you exactly
the process that I use to
actually cancel these units out.
Remember opposites cancel when we're
showing these, so let those units guide
you to get you to that final answer.
All right, let's look
at our first example.
First problem is acid base neutralization,
which is a type of double replacement
reaction, meaning that you have an acid
which is always led with an H in front
of the name reacting with a base that has
a hydroxide ion at the end of the name.
So this one's all about
finding the volume.
So when, what it's asking is how many
liters of 0.1 molar HCL can be neutralized
with 0.10 grams of magnesium hydroxide.
So one thing to kind of point
out is some key words here.
One is the word neutralized.
If you see that word that's telling you
that the reaction is going to completion,
and that is essentially just letting
you know, hey, that this is reacting.
Uh, these are the two things that are
going to be, uh, reacting together.
So what we have here is we have
HCl, which is the first part that
we see, and it says that it's
reacting with magnesium hydroxide.
So the very first step that we have to
do is we need to balance and predict.
the chemical equation.
Now, as I kind of mentioned
before, these are mainly all
double replacement reactions.
So how can you kind of
quickly identify them?
Well, you whip out essentially your
different types of chemical recipes.
Where we assign ions with letters, so
hydrogen is an A, chlorine is a B, and
then we add that to magnesium, which is
C, and then the hydroxide OH ion is D.
So we see A plus CD.
So now the way these always
bond together is inside out.
So the inside bond together
and the outside bond together.
So, our first part is going to be
pretty much H and OH are going to be
bonding together, so making H2O, so
H and then OH, we'll write that down.
This will make it a little bit easier
to balance as by kind of representing
that, but keep in mind when you have HOH,
that's just water in disguise, it's H2O.
Then the inside bond together,
which is magnesium chloride.
Now, when we are trying to balance these
different pieces, What one trick is,
is using the polyatomics to balance.
Meaning that if you look on the right hand
side of this equation, we see a hydroxide.
There's two of them.
So that means that you need two
hydroxides on the right hand
side over here to Mount Match.
Now this is why I write H
two Os, HOH, because it helps
illustrate the OH ion here.
It makes it a little bit easier to see.
So being that we have two ohs on the left,
we also need to have two ohs on the right.
So let's do that.
We'll all add it to here.
So now that we are doing that, what
we're now going to do is look at the
different ions that are here as well.
So being that we just did OH, we're
going to kind of zigzag to its
partner and look at the hydrogens.
Being that we separated these two, we have
two hydrogens, and we only have one on the
left hand side, so I'm going to add a two
over here to balance out the hydrogens.
Then as we can see, we'll
zigzag over to chlorine.
We see that we have two of them now.
How many do we have on
the right hand side?
We can see we have two over there.
So everything is now balanced and happy.
This is a balanced chemical equation.
All right.
Now our next step of what we're going
to be doing is we need to write down the
given information and include all mole
ratios that are important in the problem.
So when we do that, what we got to
do is read carefully what we have.
Okay.
we see that we have 0.
10 moles of HCl.
So with that, what we're going to do is
write that down, and the thing that's
really always important is trying
to make sure we We write everything
down underneath of the different
parts of our chemical equation.
Then what we are going to do now is we
are going to re copy all of the pieces
of information that are really important.
The first part was 0.
1 molar HCl.
We're going to write that under
HCl so that way it stays with it.
Now the next part of information that
was really important was how many
grams of magnesium hydroxide we have.
Right, as we can see that we had 0.
10 grams, so we're going to write that
underneath of our magnesium hydroxide.
And what it's asking is how
much volume of HCl you have.
So what we'll do is we'll put a
V is equal to a question mark.
Right underneath that and that will
help guide our thinking now from there
What we'll now do is we need to try
to let the units guide your thinking
and thinking Okay, well, where do I
start do I start with the molarity
which is a conversion factor, right?
You have to remember that molarity
M is e is moles over liters, right?
Meaning you can flip
it one way or another.
How do you decide which way it goes?
Versus, grams is a term by itself, so
there's no possible way for you to.
Flip that fractionally when it comes
to this math here, um, because if you
do flip it, it's going to lead to the
units being in the denominator and
it's not going to make a lot of sense.
So what we're going to start
with then first is our mass.
And well, what can we
always convert these to?
Well, if you kind of can remember, what
is your goal in terms of conversions?
It's always the mole.
Can you convert mass to moles?
And one way that you can always
do that as well, let's use.
molar mass.
So what we're going to do is take 0.
10 grams of magnesium
hydroxide and convert that to
moles using our molar mass.
So what we'll do is we'll look up
our value in our, from our periodic
table, and this is going to allow
us to calculate what that is.
So you'll take one magnesium
added to two, into two hydroxides.
And you'll get about 58.
306 grams for every one mole
of hydroxyl, or of, of MgOH.
All right, so now that we have
that, what's the most important
part of that is now that we see
that our units are going to cancel.
Grams is going to cancel grams,
and now we have it in moles.
But the thing is that we really
want is we want to figure out
what the volume is of HCl.
So how do we go to that next step?
Well, we have to convert
it to moles of HCl.
So what we're now going to do
is we're going to take this
conversion, kind of bring it down.
We'll make it a little
smaller for ourselves.
Um, if it wants to cooperate.
And how can we convert
this to moles of HCl?
Well this is where the chemical
equation is really important.
As we can see here by reading
it, we have one mole of magnesium
hydroxide to every two moles of HCl.
So what we're going to do
is do that one to two ratio.
We're going to use the chemical equation.
One mole of MgOH is equivalent
to two moles of HCl.
Now what that's going to give us is
how many moles of HCl are in this
particular reaction, which is one
of the, the most important parts.
Now, are we done?
Well, we want liters.
So how do we get to liters from here?
Well, in order to get to the
volume, which is the last step,
we can use the molarity, right?
So we can, what we can essentially do
is take that answer from the top here,
And we are going to essentially multiply
that by, or sorry, divide that by the
molarity to cancel out our numbers.
From earlier we had 0.
10 molarity.
Well, what we're going
to be doing is taking 0.
10 moles over one liter because
that's equivalent to molarity, right?
0.
10 big M is the same thing
as saying one point or 0.
10 moles.
all over one liter.
They're equivalent.
So as a result, what we can do is
try to follow our numbers so that
we can see moles, cancelled moles.
And then our moles of HCl cancelled
moles of HCl, okay, so that all
cancels, leading us with only liters.
So just to kind of clean up
the math here, how would this
all work in your calculator?
We would take 0.
1, times it by 1, times by 2 moles, then
times by 1 liter, and then we would divide
it by what's on bottom, which is 58.
306, it equals, and then divide it by 0.
1.
So what we would get for our final
answer in the end is gonna be
0.0343 liters, which we can then
convert to milliliters, right?
So Dev, so essentially multiply
that number by a thousand, and
we would get 34.3 milliliters.
So that would be how much volume it
takes to neutralize, which is about
how much it makes sense, right?
Because something that's being able to be
done in the lab, something you measure.
So as you can see with these problems,
they're a little bit more involved, they
take a little bit more time, but it's
something that you can guide your way
through, through your units cancelling.
Let's take a look at another example.
Even though gasoline in the U.
S.
no longer contains lead, this metal still
persists in the environment as a toxin.
Despite its toxicity, many paint
pigments still contain lead.
What volume of 1.
50 molar lead 2 acetate contains 0.
400 moles of lead 2 plus one?
Well, a lot of times when we're dealing
with solutions, we have to actually
understand dissociation equations.
So with this particular one, we
have lead to acetate, which means
that you have lead to plus, right?
That Roman numeral, numeral two
means two plus, not the subscript.
And we have that with the acetate
anion, which is C2H3O2 minus.
Now with this we gotta swap drop, so
what we'll do is we'll put parentheses
around our ion and bring the two
down outside of the parentheses.
Alright, so now we have this.
What we have to do is talk about
how, what's gonna happen when this
dissociates when you put it into water.
How is it going to fall apart?
Well this is where it breaks down
into it's ions, which are lead 2 plus.
And then we have the two acetate anions.
So we'd write C2H3, 2
and there's two of them.
The problem, what is being
given here, is we have a couple
important pieces of information.
One, we have that we started with 0.
400 moles of lead.
And then it's asking us,
what is the volume of that 0.
150 molarity or molar led to acetate.
So what exactly should we start with?
What is the term by itself?
So if you remember, molarity
is a conversion term.
Moles is something that's by itself.
So probably the thing that's going to
make the most sense is starting with
moles because it's a number that you
can leave in the numeral and we can
use to can, we can easily flip it.
So let's start with that.
Alright, so if I have moles of
lead 2 plus ion, what we want to do
is figure out what our volume is.
So how can we convert it to molarity,
which is your other term here, right?
Molarity is moles over liters.
So in order to bridge that gap, we
can use our chemical, our dissociation
equation that we wrote here.
And that's that one mole.
of lead 2 plus is
equivalent to one mole of
PbC2H3O2.
It's a very big formula.
Alright, so now when we do that, well,
how can we bridge the gap to liters?
So that gives us moles to moles.
Now, we can use our molarity for the
last little bit to get the liters,
which as we kind of pointed out
in the problem, is that we have 0.
150 molar or moles, and that's
equivalent to every one liter.
So what we'll do here is do 0.
4 divided by 0.
150, and we will get our final number.
And we will have that, we'll have about 0.
267 liters or about 267 moles.
milliliters of our, of our solution here.
That's going to have this
much lead inside of it.
Okay.
So being that the problem did not specify
which units we would leave it in the
SI unit, but if you had to convert it
to milliliters, you could do that too.
Let's look at our next problem, which
is a continuation of what we have here.
So with this following problem,
we're going to be doing a limiting
reactant or a limiting reagent
problem, focusing around precipitation.
So when you have two solutions mixed
together, it's a very realistic
possibility that you will have a solid
or maybe even a gas that results as one
of the products, meaning you have to
combine it with the different parts of
stoichiometry, whether it's mass to mass
stoichiometry or gas law stoichiometry.
So with this one is when the volume of 1.
50 molar lead acetate, and meaning that
it says this volume, it's referring to
the one that we solved in the previous
problem, reacts with 125 milliliters of 3.
40 molar NaCl.
How many grams of solid lead to acid, lead
to chloride are made from the reaction?
And I have the reaction shown
here that is balanced to save us a
little bit of time in this video.
So when we have this, what
are we going to start with?
Well, the first thing is you
want to stay organized with
all your pieces of information.
So the very first thing is that
being that it is a limiting reagent
problem, how do we know that it is?
Well, generally the telltale sign is
when you are given both the volume
and molarity for each solution.
So we were given a volume of 0.
267 liters with 1.
50 molar, and then on the other hand
we were given 125 milliliters of NaCl.
With 3.
40 molar NaCl.
So we were given both starting
volumes and concentrations.
You need both in order to
be able to solve for moles.
You need to be able to cancel
out the liters component.
So with that, what we are going
to do first as well, we need to
solve for the number of moles
of each individual ingredient.
Because we want to know how much lead
chloride was made in the problem.
So we're going to convert both of
these guys, essentially starting
with their volume for both.
Convert them to moles for each of
them, so go from liters to moles.
Then what we will do is go
to moles of the product.
We're going to compare both of them.
Whichever one makes less
is our limiting reactant.
So, the first one that we'll start with is
we will do it with, um, our lead acetate.
So what did we have to begin with?
We had 0.
267 liters, and we're going to cancel
that out with the molarity, which
was 1 liter is equivalent to 1.
50 molar lead acetate.
So let's kind of copy and paste that down.
Okay, so we're going to
just put that above here.
So that's of lead acetate.
All right, now what we will then
do is we're going to convert
that to moles of lead chloride.
So by reading our chemical
equation, we see that for every
one mole of lead acetate, we also
have one mole of lead chloride.
And that's using the coefficients to help
guide where that conversion came from.
So when we look at our chemical equation,
we see we have a one to one ratio.
Now when I solve that, what I am
going to end up getting is about 0.
04005 moles of lead fluoride made.
Now what that tells you is that
if you use every single milliliter
of lead fluoride, acetate.
And this is how much you're going to make
if you use up everything, if it runs out.
So this is your theoretical yield
if you run out, use everything.
However, we don't know if
that's going to be the answer.
So we got to do the same thing for NACL.
So in this case, we have 125
milliliters of NACL, and we're going
to first convert that to liters.
So we have a thousand mls is one liter.
Then we are going to use the
molarity to convert that.
So one liter is 3.
40 milliliters.
Moles of NaCl, then we'll use our
chemical formula, which is 2 moles of
NaCl is equivalent to 1 mole of lead.
Alright, so when we do the math
for this one, what we will do
is 125 divided by 1000 times 3.
40 divided by 2, and
what you will get is 0.
02125 moles of lead.
So now what we're going to do
is we're going to compare the
top value with the bottom one.
Which one is a smaller number?
That's going to be your answer because
that's going to denote your limiting
reagent So what you can see here is the
bottom one So using NaCl ran out first and
made a lot smaller of an amount Notice how
it's about approximately half the size.
So this is going to be your
limiting reagent Now are we done?
I wish.
So what we have to do is
now convert this to grams.
So, which is our final step.
So we're going to use our 0.
02125 moles of lead chloride.
And then how do we convert that to mass?
Is we're going to use the molar mass.
So we need to use our Piroc table to
find the molar mass of lead chloride.
Um, I already did that for us.
Which is about 278.
1 grams.
of lead chloride, and that's equivalent
to every one mole of lead chloride.
And once we do that, we'll
multiply those two numbers
together, and we will get about 5.
91 grams of lead chloride as our answer.
Okay, so that's how much precipitate
or solid should form if both of
these two chemicals mix together.
Let's go take a look at our next example.
42 milliliters of 0.
35 molar Ki solutions required to
completely react with 50 chloride.
of lead nitrate solution.
What is the original
concentration of lead nitrate?
So whenever you see what is the
concentration, this tends to
sometimes confuse students because
they're not sure what to look for.
Now, is it, that's what we're thinking?
Well, concentration usually
refers to molarity in chemistry.
It can refer to percent concentrations
as well as molality as well, but nine
times out of ten it's referring to
molarity unless it's specified otherwise.
So the first thing we need to do is define
our chemical equation, uh, and balance it.
So what we have is Ki is going to react
with lead nitrate, meaning that we'll
have inside reacting with outside.
So the first thing we're going to do
is being that we have lead to nitrate.
is that we will take lead as our
inside and we're going to bond it
with, with I, which there are two
iodines to help balance that, right?
So we swap drop both those charges.
Now potassium, which is a plus one charge
is going to bond with nitrate, which is
a negative one charge of K and O three.
Now when we are balancing these,
one of the easiest tricks is
balance the Polyatomics first,
meaning that if you see on the left
hand side, I have two nitrates.
Now on the right hand side
right here, I have one nitrate.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going
to put a two in front of KNO three.
The nitrates are now balanced.
I'm now gonna take a
look at the potassiums.
I'll put a two over here.
And now the entire problem
is now balanced as a result.
All we have to do is kind
of zigzag back and forth.
Make it easy to balance.
Start with the polyatomics.
What we now have to do is write
down whatever our important piece
of information, and we want to
try to include all mole ratios.
So what I'm going to do is I'm
going to move this little step down.
And we're going to write all this
down below our chemical reaction
to help us stay organized.
The first thing is, is that
we had 42 milliliters of Ki
with a concentration of 0.
35 molar.
Now, the other part that we were
given is that we have 50 milliliters
of lead nitrate, but we don't know
what the concentration is, which
is the missing part that we have.
So and that's what we're
trying to figure out.
So where exactly should
we start this problem?
Well, we want to let the units guide our
process now, but there's a little trick to
knowing this is that the side you always
start with is the one that contains.
both the volume and the molarity.
It has to have both of those pieces
because you need to convert two moles.
And the only way you can do that
is if you have molarity and you
have the volume to cancel out
the liters component of molarity.
So we're going to start
right here on the KI side.
when we are doing these different,
different, different, uh, conversions.
And we always want to start with
the term by itself, which in
this case is the volume, right?
So we'll start with the 42 milliliters
when we convert this problem.
So we'll take 42 milliliters and
we'll convert that to liters.
So that way we can get to using our
molarity, which is our next term.
So if you remember, 1, 000 mLs
is equivalent to one liter.
And then what we're then going to do
is use, convert that to moles using
molarity, which as you can remember, if
you see in the top left of your screen,
is that one liter is equivalent to 0.
35 moles.
of our Ki solution.
So we want to label what the
solution is so we don't get mixed up.
Now what we're going to use is the
chemical equation here, and what
we can see is that 2 is equivalent
to 1 mole of lead nitrate.
That is from your chemical formula.
So we have 2 moles of Ki, and that's
equivalent to 1 mole of lead nitrate.
Alright, so that gets us to moles, right?
Our goal is always the mole.
Now, what we'll do is we're going
to calculate how many moles there
are, and then in order to get this
into molarity, so if you remember,
molarity is moles over liters.
This first portion will give
us how many moles there are.
The liter component is, if you remember,
we started with 50 milliliters, which
is how much the problem told us we have.
We'll divide that, uh, we'll
convert that to liters and then
divide this number by that.
When we do the math here, what
we are going to be getting,
so we'll take 42 times 0.
35, divide it by 1, 000, divide
it by 2, and we will get 0.
00735 moles of lead nitrate.
And what we are going to then do is we're
going to take that number and divide it
by 50 milliliters converted to liters.
So it's going to be 0.
0735.
Divided by 0.
05 liters.
Okay, so that 50 ml gets converted.
Now once we solve that, what we'll
get for our final answer is 0.
147 liters as our final answer.
And we have three sig figs because
we started with three sig figs.
And that's how you would solve essentially
going through the entire process, how
to figure out how much volume there is.
So what did this video show you?
We went through how to find volume, we
went to find mass, how to find molarity.
And the biggest thing was how to
use molarity as a conversion term,
using balanced chemical equations
and how to use mole maps to
help guide your thinking, right?
This whole process is a long one, but
it's something that it, the more you
practice it, the easier it's going to get.
And you can see stoichiometry
is all about how can you really
make those units cancel, right?
As you go through them.
If this video helped you, I appreciate it.
And if it didn't make, if it made it as
a little confusing, please ask questions
and let me know if you need help.
I'm always here for you.
Please either send me a message.
Email me or reach out to me, or if
you want to, you can even comment
in the videos below and let me know
what you thought, or if you have a
question in particular, or if you can
find an error, that's always okay too.
Uh, and, and if this is your first
time here, please like this video
and subscribe to the channel for
more introductory chemistry content
to help you guys pass chemistry.
All right.
Thank you so much.
And I hope to see you all next time.
Bye now.